Edgecliff College Schweitzer-Preminger Collection
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Edgecliff College Schweitzer-Preminger Collection
1949-1976
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Edgecliff College
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
This is a small collection of photographs, correspondence and published materials about both Dr. Albert Schweitzer and Marion Mill Preminger, a graduate of Our Lady of Cincinnati (later named Edgecliff College). The collection covers in part the association of Schweitzer and Preminger in Dr. Schweitzer's medical missionary work in Africa. The materials originally were part of an exhibit done by Edgecliff College.
XUA-52
History of Schweitzer-Preminger Collection
The Schweitzer-Preminger Collection originated at Edgecliff College, Cincinnati, Ohio to honor both Dr. Albert Schweitzer, the famous humanitarian and physician, and Marion Mill Preminger, an alumna of Our Lady of Cincinnati College (later called Edgecliff College). Preminger was a noted socialite and authoress. She was also an associate of Dr. Albert Schweitzer in his medical missionary work in Africa.
When Edgecliff College closed in the 1980's Xavier University Library acquired the collection, including many books. In order to foster greater use of the collection, Xavier University Library transferred much of the collection to the Albert Schweitzer Center in Great Barrington, MA..The items represented in the present collection are believed to be originally part of an exhibit sponsored by Edgecliff College. The components of the collection were given in large part to Edgecliff College by Albert Mayer, the husband of Marion Mill Preminger. Some publications and other printed materials found in the collection were given to Edgecliff College by Albert Mayer. Other materials were assembled by librarians at Edgecliff College.
Scope and Content
This collection highlights the work of Dr. Albert Schweitzer and the participation of Marion Mill Preminger in his work. The collection includes the correspondence of Albert Mayer to Dr. Dorothy Weil of Edgecliff College concerning his wife Marion Mill Preminger. Also included are photographs of both Dr. Schweitzer and Preminger, publications by and about both Schweitzer and Preminger, and some personal mementos of Preminger (including publications inscribed to her by Dr. Schweitzer).
Marion Mill Preminger was a distinguished alumna of Our Lady of Cincinnati College, later named Edgecliff College.
Statement of Arrangement
The collection is divided into the following series and subseries: Series I.: Albert Mayer Correspondence concerning Marion Mill Preminger Series II.: Photographs Subseries 1.: Preminger and Schweitzer photographs in Gunsbach, Alsance and at Lambarne Hospital in Gabon Subseries 2.: Preminger photographs, principally in New York Subseries 3.:Photographs of the Schweitzer Symposium at Edgecliff College Series III.: Publications by Dr. Schweitzer and inscribed to Marion Mill Preminger Series IV.: Publications by and about Dr. Albert Schweitzer and Marion Mill Preminger Subseries 1.: Publications by Dr. Albert Schweitzer (articles,booklets, and reprints) Subseries 2.: Publications about Dr. Albert Schweitzer (articles, booklets, reprints, and news clippings) Subseries 3.: Publications and unpublished works by Marion Mill Preminger Subseries 4.: Articles about Marion Mill Preminger Series V.: Items relating to the Edgecliff College Schweitzer-Preminger Collection and Symposium at Edgecliff College Series VI. Mementos
Acquisition Information
Materials in this collection were acquired by Xavier University Library as part of the purchase agreement with Edgecliff College.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Preminger, Marion Mill; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965; Edgecliff College--Alumni and alumnae
Persons:
Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965; Preminger, Marion Mill; Mayer, Albert, 1897-1981
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Series I.: Albert Mayer Correspondence concerning Marion Mill Preminger, 1964, 1972, 1976, undated
  This is an extensive letter written by Albert Mayer to Dr. Dorothy Weil of Edgecliff College in which he gives a series of "vignettes" that described his late wife Marion Mill Preminger. The correspondence is dated May 10, 1976. Included with each "vignette" are attachments (photographs and other documentation).
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Cover Letter, 1976 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #1, 1976 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #2, 1976 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #2, Attachments "Apartment Museums;" "Apartment Library" (Two Photographs), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #3, 1976 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #3 Attachment: "A Festive Jubilee..." (Article), 1972 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #3 Attachments: "Elegance" (Two Photographs), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #3 Attachment: "Gabonese Consulate Kids Party" (Three Photographs), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #4, 1976 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #4 Attachment: Letter from Jane B. Spain to Albert Mayer (photocopy), 1972 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #4 Attachment: "Dr. Marion Mill Preminger Award..." (Article), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Albert Meyer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #4 Attachment: "Apartment Museum" (Article), 1964 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Albert Mayer Correspondence to Dr. Dorothy Weil Vignette #4 Attachment: Letter from Anita Loos to Albert Mayer, 1972 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II.: Photographs, 1954-1975; undated
  - Sub-Series 1.: Preminger and Schweitzer Photographs in Gunsbach, Alsance and at Lambarne Hospital in Gabon, 1954-1962; undated
    - Marion Mill Preminger and Dr. Albert Schweitzer in Schweitzer's Hometown of Gunsbach, Alsance (13 Photographs), 1954; undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      These photographs were taken by Richard Kik.
    - Dr. Schweitzer and Marion Mill Preminger with Animal Friends in Lambarene (2 Photographs), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Settlement and Hospital at Lambarene with Marion Mill Preminger and Dr. Albert Schweitzer (10 Photographs), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Marion Mill Preminger in Lambarene (Includes Photograph with Dr. Schweitzer) (9 Photographs), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - President Leon Mba Presentation of Award to Dr. Albert Schweitzer and Marion Mill Preminger (5 Photographs), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Marion Mill Preminger with the African Children in the Leper Village in Lambarene (2 Photographs), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Dr. Albert Schweitzer Delivering Nobel Prize Address and at His Hospital (Microcard Negative), 1954; undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sub-Series 2.: Preminger Photographs Taken Chiefly in New York, 1959; 1970; undated
    - Marion Mill Preminger Seated with Her Primitive African Art Collection, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
      This photo shows the primitive African art collection and leopard skin floor coverings displayed in the living room and dining room of Preminger's apartment in New York City.
    - Preminger Primitive African Art Collection, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Marion Mill Preminger with Her Primitive African Art Collection, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Marion Mill Preminger in Her Apartment Library, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Preminger's library included elegant Aubusson-covered chairs, rugs, icons, and rare books.
    - Marion Mill Preminger with African Visitors in Her Library, 1964, 1972, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Marion Mill Preminger with Mrs. Ligea Bielukas of the Baltic Nations Women's Club, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Mrs. Bielukas was an annual visitor of Preminger.
    - Marion Mill Preminger with Dr. E. Gaine Cannon at the Albert Schweitzer Memorial Hospital, Balsam Grove, NC, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
      This photo shows Preminger with Dr.E. Gaine Cannon. Preminger helped him set up the Albert Schweitzer Memorial Hospital at Balsam Grove, NC.
    - Marion Mill Preminger with Dr. E. Gaine Cannon at the Marion Mill Preminger Obstetrical Clinic, Balsam Grove, NC, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Marion Mill Preminger as a Young Woman, with Dr. Albert Einstein, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Marion Mill Preminger with Author Thornton Wilder, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Marion Mill Preminger with Author Thornton Wilder (2 Photographs), 1959; undated; Cut outs from larger photos. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Marion Mill Preminger with Mrs. Pat Nixon in the White House, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Marion Mill Preminger with M.F. Santori (left) and M.B. Corne (right), undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
      This photo shows Preminger conferring with other members of the Committee for the Handicapped People-to-People Program
    - Marion Mill Preminger with Her African Friends at a Baptism in New York City (2 Photographs), undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Marion Mill Preminger at a Party for Children of African Consulates in her New York City Apartment (5 Photographs), undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Party for Children of African Consulates in the Preminger New York City Apartment, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Acceptance Letter of President Bongo of the Republic of Gabon of the Preminger Collection of African Art (Negative), 1970 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Preminger as Recipient of Honorary Degree at Edgecliff College, 1970; These are pages taken from the Edgecliff College Yearbook, 1970. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Sub-Series 3.: Photographs of the Schweitzer Symposium at Edgecliff College, 1975 October 26
    - Schweitzer Symposium at Edgecliff College (11 Photographs), 1975 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Series III.: Publications by Dr. Schweitzer and Inscribed to Marion Mill Preminger, 1956; 1958
  - "Die Ganze Menschheit Ist Bedroht" (Reprint), 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    A reprint from Schweizer Frauenblatt (No. 21) dated 1957. The inscription to Marion Preminger by Dr. Albert Schweitzer is dated January 29, 1958.
  - Kein Sonnenstrahl Geht Verloren: Wort Albert Schweitzers (book) (Freiburg: Hyperion-Verlag, n.d.), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    A small volume of Dr. Schweitzer's work Kein Sonnenstrahl Geth Verloren which is inscibed to Marion Preminger by Dr. Albert Schweitzer and dated 1956.This volume includes a second autograph by Dr. Schweitzer beneath his portrait on the page preceding the title page.
    A second copy of the book is included in the folder. This book bears a 10/25/1955 inscription by an unknown person to a person named Koffmann.
    Both books bear the library stamp "Schweitzer-Preminger Collection, Edgecliff College Library."
- Series IV.: Publications by and about Dr. Albert Schweitzer and Marion Mill Preminger, 1930-1975
  - Sub-series 1.: Publications by Dr. Albert Schweitzer (Articles, booklets, and reprints), 1930-1970
    - Articles by Dr. Albert Schweitzer, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Eleven published writings of Dr. Albert Schweitzer found as reprints or booklets. Some works were published by the Albert Schweitzer Education Foundation. Text is in English or German.
  - Sub-series 2.: Publications about Dr. Albert Schweitzer (articles, booklets, reprints, and news-clippings), 1949-1976
    - Writings About Dr. Albert Schweitzer (Booklets, Reprints, Serial Articles, etc.), 1949-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Twenty-Nine articles written about Dr. Albert Schweitzer and appearing in various journals, magazines, booklets, etc.). The text is in English, German, French and Dutch. This folder includes a photocopy of Albert Mayer's typescript entitled "Dr. Schweitzer's Hospital: Some Lessons for Aid to Under-Developed Countries" (dated 2/7/1962).
    - Newspaper Clippings About Dr. Albert Schweitzer, 1958-1975; undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sub-series 3.: Publications and Unpublished Works by Marion Mill Preminger, 1962-1975
    - Articles by Marion Mill Preminger, 1962-1966; undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Six writings of Marion Mill Preminger as found in serial publications or typescript manuscript.
    - Preminger Mayer Edgecliff College Commencement Address, 1970 May 31; 1975 September 26 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      This is the text of the commencement address delivered at Edgecliff College on May 31, 1970 by Marion Mill Preminger Mayer. She received an honorary degree from the college at this event.
  - Sub-series 4.: Articles about Marion Mill Preminger (includes Obituaries), 1956-1972; undated
    - Articles about Marion Mill Preminger (includes obituaries), 1956-1972; undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Twenty-one articles about Marion Mill Preminger as found in newspapers and other publication formats.
- Series V.: Items relating to the Edgecliff College Schweitzer-Preminger Collection and the 1975 Symposium at Edgecliff College, 1973-1976; undated
  - Newspaper Clippings and Other Articles about the Schweitzer-Preminger Collection, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    This is a file of local newspaper articles and articles written in Edgecliff College publications concerning the Schweitzer-Preminger Collection.
  - Bookplate: "Marion Mill Preminger, Reverence for Life", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Schweitzer Symposium at Edgecliff College: News Clippings and Assorted Information, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Albert Schweitzer Friendship House: Information and Postcards, 1974; undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    This file contains information on Erica Anderson, President of the Albert Schweitzer Friendship House. Included are postcards and holiday cards bearing Schweitzer's portrait.
  - Association Internationale de L'Hopital (AISL): Correspondence and Newsletter, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series VI. Mementos, 1965-1975; undated
  - Brandais University National Women's Committee Special Book Collection Award, undated (Box 3, Piece 1)
  - Dobbs Ferry Woman's Club Award, 1965 (Box 3, Piece 2)
  - Schweitzer-Preminger Collection Guestbook Edgecliff College, Brennan Memorial Library, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Piece 3)
  - Leather Book Case, undated (Box 3, Piece 4)
    This leather bookcase bears the image of Albert Schweitzer. The case holds some newspaper clippings.
  - Marion Mill Preminger Award Medallions, undated (Box 3, Piece 5)
    Three medallions are found in a display case.A dedication with the medallions reads: "First Coining of the Medallions to be awarded annually for Distinguished Service and proudly designated by the Committee for the Handicaped People to People Program as the Marion Mill Preminger Award honoring a dedicated woman whose lifetime of broad-visioned philanthropy has contributed significantly to the expanding of opportunities to the less fortunate."
  - Preminger Memorabilia, 1972; undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    This file contains African art postcards, paper money, a bookmarker, and a membership card.
  - Schweitzer Memorabilia, 1975; 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    This file includes Schweitzer postage stamps and an ad for the Albert Schweitzer Jubilee Book.